hello everybody
this is howie hawkins and we have a
special guest tonight
john kiriakou who is one of the
significant whistleblowers
uh and we will get to that in a minute i
first have to report some sad news
many of you met an activist here in
syracuse named nikita slade
when we had her on this live stream
angela and i to talk about
organizing and we're really in shock
here in syracuse
and around the movement because she died
suddenly
last week from a heart attack she was
only 32
and she's somebody who is active in our
syracuse green party here
she was on the staff of my 2014
campaign for new york governor she was
an advisor on
policing and racial justice issues for
our presidential campaign
and she was a key leader in black lives
matter syracuse
and she also did a queer women of color
podcast that was one of angela's
favorites
she was a union millwright but
to me she was the best activist i have
met
from her generation um
you know she was one of the most
well-read activists of any generation
i had many conversations with her on
social theory and
organizing and she'd read a lot of books
that
i i haven't found anybody else to talk
to about
so i'm gonna miss her for those
conversations as much as her
energy and commitment to the movement
and we were blessed
for the contributions she made while she
was with us
and we're just so sad that uh she's
departed and uh
she had a lot more to give so
you know that's the sad news and uh
angela and i wrote a little remembrance
on the website
if you go there under the updates you
can you can read about it there's some
pictures
there's links to the interviews i did an
interview with her after a
black glass matter demonstration here in
syracuse
and you'll see how much she was giving
and it's
you know how sad it is that she's not
with us anymore
so that's uh just sad news to report
so what we want to talk about tonight is
the war on whistleblowers
and i'm wearing my ralph nate i'm ralph
nader t-shirt from
08 if you can see that uh ralph coined
the term
whistleblowers as we understand it today
he had a big conference and a
a book you know trying to promote
people in government and in corporate
sector to release information that ought
to be
in the public domain in the public
interest
and he had a big impact um you know that
became part of the
ethic of people that wanted to you know
do good and
eventually one of the last piece of
legislation is that able to help
shepherd through congress was the
whistleblower's protection act in 1989
although that has been uh weakened by
court decisions
particularly with respect to people
releasing information that's in the
national security realm
so most of the uh
war on whistleblowers that we're
familiar with now
are people charged under the espionage
act
except they're not doing espionage
they're releasing information
that they think the public ought to know
but the espionage act was
enacted in 1917 during world war one
to go after the anti-war movement and
one of the
really debilitating repressive features
of it is
if you release information you can't
defend it
as in the public interest that's not
permitted under the statute
which makes whistleblowers for a charge
for espionage which they're not working
for any foreign government
uh it puts them in a real bind and
so back in 19 around world war one
uh they charged the antiwar radicals
emma goldman and alexander
berkman the anarchists were deported to
russia
three socialists were charged under it
one was a member of congress
victor berger another was a philip
randolph
who we know as a civil rights leader
later in the century
and then eugene debs who was actually
sentenced to 10 years
for an anti-war speech he gave in canton
ohio
i wrote a remembrance of that uh
on the anniversary i think last year uh
he ended up spending three years in jail
and then he was pardoned by president
harding who invited him to the white
house
very different than the treatment our
whistleblowers are getting today
you know harding took the place of
wilson it was rarely used for
the rest of the century a couple
espionage cases the most notable is the
rosenberg's case uh and
while julius may have been uh giving
atomic information to the russians it
seems evidence shows that
his wife ethel was not but she was
executed as well
but then it was used for the first time
against whistleblowers by richard nixon
going against
daniel ellsberg and anthony russo for
releasing the pentagon papers
and they were not convicted because of
fbi misconduct
and then it laid dormant again until
the administration of barack obama and
he went after
eight different people for leaking
information
mostly about our military and
intelligence operations
and you've heard of some of these people
chelsea manning
who released all informations including
that infamous collateral murder
video which showed this guy in a
helicopter gunship killing
civilians asking for permission seemed
to be
you know excited about it reminded me of
the first
vietnam vet i talked to back in 1964
he's the older brother of a
little league league teammate who was
bragging about how he was just
killing random people from his
helicopter in vietnam
um and that massacre not only killed
civilians but it killed
some reuters journalists and
so chelsea you know has spent time in
prison for that they've still
uh you know asked her to do more and
she's spent more time in prison
in that same first group of eight under
obama
edward snowden is probably the best
known he's somebody
his book on uh what do you call it uh
oh forget the name came out in 2019 it
was the most impactful book i read that
year
and i was saying during the campaign i
would uh
drop the charges and bring him into the
administration because i
felt he had the right values he was for
democracy against authoritarianism
and had a handle on how to do you know
proper intelligence without violating
people's
constitutional rights and you know if i
was president i would need somebody
who knew how to do that and then another
one is our guest tonight
john kiriakou who revealed to
journalists
uh information about the cia's torture
program
during the early 2000s
and then uh obama i mean trump continued
uh obama administration declined to
prosecute
julian assange trump has gone ahead and
biden has continued and there are a
number of other cases
going on right now that we'll probably
talk about tonight like daniel hale
and then the last thing i want to say
before i bring on john kiriakou
is that it's not only the espionage act
we have a case with stephen donziger
uh his he had a trial opened up
yesterday
and this is a man who worked with 30 000
farmers and indigenous people in ecuador
and won a 9.5 or 8.5 billion dollars
in damages from chevron for
environmental and health
uh damages in ecuador in 2011
and right away chevron uh sued in this
country and
uh they charge them with things like
saying he extorted and bribed and so
forth the
process in ecuador and so
by 2014 uh
he didn't get a jury trial he just had a
judge rule
that uh the ecuadorian
uh ruling should be vacated and fined
uh donziger 800 000
and uh then uh in the appeal
uh the judge asked for you know his
phone and computer and whatnot
which don said that's attorney-client
privilege
so they charged him with contempt the
court which led to his disbarment
and house arrest now march this year
the second quarter of a circuit court of
appeals
vacated some of the sanctions against
donziger i included house arrest
because of this uh contempt of court
charge so that went to trial
yesterday and already a couple of the
chevron lawyers
have dropped out because in
cross-examination
the lies they've been giving would be
exposed that's that's what the theory is
um so
now it's be in in the prosecution is
being done by a private
prosecutor because the southern district
of new york the us attorney
said there's not a case and refused to
uh
to prosecute so there's a lot of shady
stuff going on here
and uh progressive democrats just sent a
letter to
mayor garland to look into this case
it's got a lot of attention
uh people are wondering where barack
obama is he went to law school with
steven donziger they play basketball
together obama's been silent
ralph nader had a podcast that's worth
listening
i think in late march with stephen
donziger
but you can see what the issue is here
he won a big judgments again against the
corporation
and they went to the u.s courts which
acted like they're lackeys
and basically took this man's life from
him
and you know he's fighting to get it
back in court and it's a case we should
all be following so
that's what we're talking about with
whistleblowers it's really difficult to
be a whistleblower you put your whole
life
on the line and uh that book by
uh ed snowden his permanent record
uh so i had forgot that so let's
let's bring john kiryaku on and he can
talk about
his experience as a whistleblower and he
knows a lot of these whistleblowers
we haven't named all of them but
we'll get to them as we go through this
discussion so welcome john
thank you howie thanks very much for
having me and uh hello everybody
i'm uh i'm very happy to be here i've
got a story to tell you
and i'll tell the story and i'd love to
take
whatever questions you might have uh so
i
i spent 15 years at the cia the first
half of my career was in analysis just
sort of sitting at a desk thinking the
big thoughts
writing papers that nobody would read
and i got bored with that
and i made a very unusual transfer
into counter-terrorism operations
as it turned out i was the only person
in the entire cia
who was fluent in both greek and arabic
and they made a determination
that it was a lot easier to teach a
linguist operations than it was to take
an operations person and teach
teach them how to speak greek and arabic
so i went into counter terrorism
operations
in 1997
and in the immediate aftermath of the 9
11 attacks
i was named the chief of
counterterrorism
for the cia in pakistan
so in that position
high stress dangerous position
i led a series of raids in march of 2002
that resulted in the capture of
well i'm not allowed to say the actual
number still but it was many dozens
of al-qaeda fighters including one by
the name of abu zubaydah
who we believed at the time was the
number three in al qaeda
he was not the number three he was
actually never even a member of al qaeda
he was certainly a bad guy he
uh assisted al qaeda in terms of
logistics you know if
if you were tired of the fight and you
wanted to take it home
abu zubaydah would get it for you abu
zubaydah created and ran the two
al-qaeda training camps in southern
afghanistan he
formed the uh what was called the house
of martyrs
safe house in peshawar pakistan so bad
guy but not
a member of al qaeda and certainly not
the number three in al qaeda
but on the night of march 22nd 2002 we
we caught him
and a pakistani policeman shot him three
times with an ak-47
in the thigh the groin and the stomach
and
he was very severely wounded
my orders were to
sit next to his bed 24 7.
george tenet told me 24 7
cia eyes on he said do not leave his
bedside
and so i i sat there 24 hours after we
caught him
abu zabeda came out of his coma
and the first thing he said to me was he
asked me to
kill him he asked me to take a pillow
and smother him
and i said i said oh no abu zubato
we've been we've been looking for you
for a long time
nobody's going to kill you in fact i
said you're going to get the best
medical care that the american
government
could provide he cried a lot
he said that he would never know the
touch of a woman
he would never know the joy of
fatherhood and um and we talked a lot
about religion uh he
recited poetry he asked if i would pass
a message to his mother
and finally i said listen i'm going to
give you some advice
i am the nicest guy that you're going to
meet in this experience
my colleagues are not nice like i am
so if there's one thing that you do it's
that you have to cooperate
there were 50 000 people in those towers
that morning
i said you're not the victim here
and he said to me you seem like a nice
man
but you're the enemy and i'll never
cooperate
so another well altogether 56 hours
passed i was with him for 56 hours and
um and uh
a cia plane flew in to pick him up and
take him to what turned out to be a
secret prison
that none of us knew about we we didn't
have a need to know and we weren't
read into the uh into the compartment
so he asked me to hold his hand three
fbi agents and i carried him out
to the plane on uh on a gurney and uh
we we tied him across the luggage rack
at the back of the plane
and i leaned over and i said remember
you have to cooperate
good luck i told him and i squeezed his
hand never saw him again
three months later i've returned to cia
headquarters
and um certainly abu zubaydah was not
cooperating but i was in the cafeteria
one day
standing in line to get lunch and a
senior officer from the cia's
counterterrorism center
stopped me and said hey very casually
hey i'm glad i ran into you
do you want to be certified in the use
of enhanced interrogation techniques
i had never heard that term before this
was our this was
sorry may the sixth two thousand two i
still remember the date
so i said enhanced interrogation
techniques techniques
what does that mean and very excitedly
he he said we're going to start getting
rough with these guys
and i said well what exactly does that
mean and so he explained to me
these different techniques and i said
man that sounds like a torture program
i i've got a i've got a moral and
ethical problem with that besides the
fact
that torture is illegal the fact of the
matter is
we have something in this country called
the federal torture act of 1946
which specifically outlaws specifically
outlaws exactly those techniques that we
used against al qaeda prisoners
besides that we were signatories too
and the drafters of the united nations
convention against torture
now in 1946 we executed japanese
soldiers
who waterboarded american pows that was
a death penalty
crime to waterboard somebody
in 1968 january 11 1968
the washington post ran a front page
photograph of an american soldier
waterboarding
a north vietnamese prisoner on the day
that that photo appeared
secretary of defense mcnamara ordered an
investigation
the soldier was arrested he was charged
with torture and he was sentenced to 20
years
in prison well the law never changed
we changed so something that was
a death penalty offense in 1946
something that called for 20 years in
prison
in 1968 was not just okay
by 2002 it was actively encouraged and
supported by both
the justice department and the white
house and then carried out by the
central intelligence agency
i said this was illegal it was immoral
and it was unethical and i wanted no
part of it on august 1st
2002 the cia began to torture abu zubair
and they began
with the technique of waterboarding
which was one of the the harshest
uh techniques that they had
certainly there were people inside the
cia who objected to this but
the key phrase here is inside the cia
nobody said anything
publicly nothing not a word i was
promoted at the time because i had
caught up with a beta
and so i became the executive assistant
to the cia's deputy director for
operations and in that capacity i saw
literally every cable that was coming
into the cia from around the world
and so i was reading the reporting
coming back
from the secret site where abu zabada
had been taken
and cia officers went far beyond
what had been authorized by uh
by the justice department there were a
couple of techniques that they were
using that i believed
at the time and still to this day that
were worse than
uh than waterboarding one was
sleep deprivation now sleep deprivation
sounds like no big deal right they keep
you awake
but it's not that simple what they do is
they
they chain you to an eye bolt in the
ceiling so you can't sit or
kneel or lay or get comfortable in any
way
they have industrial power lights
on you 24 hours a day and they're
blasting
music over and over and over the same
song
over and over again 24 hours a day
now we know from the american
psychological association the apa which
has done studies on these kinds of
things
that people begin to lose their minds
around day
seven with no sleep they begin to
die around day nine and that's because
your organs begin to shut down from lack
of sleep
the cia though was authorized to keep
prisoners awake for up to 12
days now we killed people with that
technique of sleep deprivation
there was nothing in the justice
department's opinion that said we could
murder people
but they did it anyway um the other one
was was called the cold cell the cold
cell was an
absolutely horrible thing they chain you
to that eye bolt in the ceiling again
they chill your cell to 50 degrees
fahrenheit
they strip you naked and then every hour
a cia officer goes into your cell and
throws a bucket of ice water on you
we killed two more prisoners with that
technique
so this was ongoing and
at the same time the cia was collecting
literally
no intelligence from any of these
prisoners
you know certainly they were babbling on
about
whatever it was they thought the cia
wanted to hear just to get them to stop
the torture
but they were not able the the analysts
and the collectors were not able to
collect any
actionable intelligence at all nothing
i resigned from the cia in
uh early 2004 and um
i i was waiting for somebody to say
something
because i i just assumed that you know
this was so heinous
and there were certainly other people
inside the agency that were opposed to
it i just
expected somebody to come out and say
something nobody said a word finally in
december of 2007 five and a half
years after i got home from pakistan
and more than five years after we
started torturing abu zabeda
i got a call from brian ross at abc news
and he said that someone had told him
a source had told him that
i had tortured up zubaida i said that
was absolutely untrue
i was the only person who was kind to
abu zabeda
i have never raised a hand to a prisoner
in my life i said your source is either
mistaken or he's lying and i came to the
conclusion later that the source was
lying
because it turned out the source was at
the white house so i decided
that now was the time to come clean that
the american people
owned this information the american
people
had a right to know what their
government was doing
in their name besides the fact that it
is illegal it is a felony to classify
a crime and what i mean by that is
if you are doing something that is a
crime whether in the united states
or under international law it is illegal
to make that operation classified
by definition because it's a crime it
has to remain
unclassified and so on december 11 2007
i gave a nationally broadcast
interview with brian ross at abc news
and i said three things
that just changed the course of the rest
of my life
i said that the cia was torturing its
prisoners
i said that torture was official u.s
government policy
it was not the result of a rogue cia
officer as president bush had said
disingenuously and i said that the
torture program had been
personally approved by the president
himself
as you might imagine within 24 hours the
cia
reported me to the fbi they filed
something called a crimes report
saying that i had leaked classified
information to the media
the fbi investigated me for a full year
from december of 2007 until december of
and then they sent my attorney something
called a declination letter
declining to prosecute me they said that
i had
not violated the law
four weeks later barack obama becomes
president
and he appoints john brennan an old
nemesis of mine
to be the deputy national security
adviser for counterterrorism
i had no idea that john brennan
secretly asked the justice department to
reopen the case against me
and so for the next three years my
phones were tapped
my emails were intercepted and teams of
fbi agents followed me not all the time
but followed me periodically
wherever to the grocery store to church
to a restaurant with my family they
followed me to my to my mom's sister's
funeral in ohio i actually didn't know
it was them
um and i reported it to the fbi thinking
maybe it's a terrorist maybe it's a
criminal you know who knows here it was
the fbi and i reported it to the fbi
so in january
2012 this all came to a head
and i was arrested and charged with
five felonies including three counts of
espionage
now as howie pointed out espionage
is one of the gravest crimes with which
an american can be charged
and in many cases it carries with it the
death penalty
i knew in my heart i hadn't committed
espionage
talking to abc news or really talking to
the american people
via abc news is not espionage
and so i hired a team of
a list nationally known
national security attorneys here in
washington and we decided
we were going to fight now let's talk
about that espionage act for a minute
howie mentioned that the espionage act
was
was written and passed into law in 1917
the the stated purpose at the time was
to combat german saboteurs during the
first world war
uh it was never used against german
saboteurs it was used against
progressives and anti-war activists
but between 1917 and 2009
the espionage act was used to prosecute
three people
who had spoken to the media right
how we mentioned correctly that it was
used against other
political opponents of whatever uh
president happened to be in office but
three people were prosecuted for
speaking to the media
just under barack obama eight
americans were charged with espionage
for speaking to the media
barack obama had what i would describe
as
a nixonian obsession with leaks
the new york times said that the point
of
my prosecution was not even really to
prosecute me
it was not even really to punish me it
was to frighten
every other person in the national
security apparatus
from going to the public from going to
the press
to discuss waste fraud abuse illegality
or threats to the public health or
public safety which is the definition of
whistleblowing the legal definition
and certainly scott shane at the new
york times
told me that on the day of my arrest
every single one of the new york times
national security sources went silent
and stayed silent uh
it's kind of a long story but i'm gonna
skip a lot of it and we could talk about
it in the questions and answers
what ended up happening was this
i was facing 45 years in prison
in my first meeting with the justice
department that's what they offered me
45 years and one of the justice
department's lawyers said
take the plea mr kiriakou and you may
live to meet your grandchildren
i said i'm not doing 45 minutes
later on they came down to 10 years on a
monday
10 years they said take a guilty plea to
espionage and do 10 years
i said i didn't commit espionage and i
haven't done
anything to be ashamed of on wednesday
two days later they came down to eight
years
and then on friday they came down to
five years
my lead attorney was a giant by the name
of plato caceres
and plato said these were his exact
words
i've been a practicing attorney in
washington for 52 years
and he said i've never seen them come
down in time
he said usually they'll offer you 10 if
you turn it down
they offer you 15 if you turn it down
they offer you 18.
and i said well why are they coming down
in time with me
and very quickly he said because they
have a case and they know it's
so i said well what do we do he said we
fight and we go to trial
you didn't do anything wrong the truth
of the matter is
according to propublica which did a
study published in
november of 2012 the federal government
wins
98.2 percent of its cases
almost all of those are a result of two
techniques
that the justice department uses one is
called charge stacking
and the other is venue shopping now
venue shopping is easy they charge you
in the federal district where you are
most likely to be convicted
and where you are most likely to get a
long sentence
that's why i was charged in the eastern
district of virginia it's called the
espionage
court because no national security
defendant has ever won a case there
that's where they charge jeffrey
sterling that's where they charged
chelsea manning that's where they
charged well chelsea manning
was military but her um her contempt
was eastern district that's where they
charged ed snowden
and julian assange
the other one i said is charge stacking
so what they'll do is they'll charge you
let's say maybe you did do something
wrong
but they won't charge you with one crime
they'll charge you with 10
20 felonies and they'll wait until you
go bankrupt
and then they'll come and say all right
listen we'll drop all the charges if you
plead guilty to one felony
well what are you gonna do i had five
kids at home
i knew that they won 98.2 percent of
their cases
i was facing 45 years in prison they're
offering me now their final their best
and final
offer was two and a half years i do 23
months
so i hired o.j simpson's
jury consultant who happened to be the
uncle of my best friend's
wife uh no eastern district of virginia
is
in alexandria virginia uh in response to
one of the questions so i hired the jury
consultant
and he came up and we got him we got him
a security clearance because all my
lawyers had to be cleared
he went through all 15 000 pages of
discovery
and then we all met in this big
conference room and he said
if we were in any other district in
america
we would win this thing he said but the
eastern district of virginia
your jury is going to be made up of
people from the
fbi the cia the pentagon
intelligence community contractors and
their family members he said you don't
have a prayer
just take the deal the night before i
had to give
the justice department an answer my wife
and i stayed up
all night long i was only the second
american ever charged with violating the
intelligence identities protection act
of 1981 and so
we went over there was no case law but
uh there were several um law review
journals from harvard law school
and we concluded that i just hadn't done
anything wrong i hadn't broken the law
and so i emailed my attorneys at six
o'clock in the morning and i said
i've been thinking about it all night
and i decided i want to go to trial
thinking stupidly
that once i got in front of a jury they
would see how ridiculous this was
they'd see that it was political they
would see that i had
done a public service and my lawyers
called me and said or one of them called
me and said put on a pot of coffee we're
on the way over
they came over to my house they told me
you can't turn this down
you have to take the deal if you're
convicted
you're seriously looking at 12 to 18
years
just take the deal i still didn't want
to take the deal
and then one of the attorneys the one
who i liked and respected the most
um pulled me aside and said listen
this can be a blip in your life or it
can be the defining
event in your life make it the blip
and so i took the deal um
it's funny that that the deal
the case itself made me far
better known than i ever would have been
before
i mean when i blew the whistle on the
torture program it was a story for
a few days a week but my but my
prosecution made me
a martyr for human rights it gave me
a a venue a soapbox
with which i could speak to the american
people i'm on tv all the time
thanks to these idiots at the at the
justice department
otherwise you know nobody would even
remember
that there was a guy who said anything
about the the torture program
i was very pleased one day when i was
sitting in prison it was
it was december of 2014 and i was
reading a four-day-old copy of the new
york times they would of course
go through my new york times and cut out
articles that they didn't want me to
read
but there was an interview in there with
uh with ed snowden
and ed said that he had watched my case
and he had watched tom drake's case
tom drake the nsa whistleblower and
neither one of us
backed down despite the the enormous
pressure that we were under
and so we had inspired him to go public
with his
revelations and i gotta tell you that
and one other thing that also happened
in december of 14 made it all worthwhile
the other thing was i'm sitting there in
my cell one day
and a guy walks in and says hey buddy
you're on tv
i said oh okay i got up i walked over
the tv
and it was john mccain standing on the
floor of the senate
saying that without my revelations the
american people would never have known
that there was a torture program and
that they were torturing people
in the name of the american people he
said even though i was in prison
that i deserved the thanks of the
american public
and he was happy to do that from the
floor of the senate
that completely changed the way that i
saw myself
you know cnn until the day before i went
to prison called me
cia leaker john kiriakou they changed it
to cia torture whistleblower john
kiriakou the day before i went to prison
fox for whatever odd reason probably
because i was prosecuted by obama
always called me cia torture
whistleblower
john kiriakou msnbc which was you know
pretty much the obama network
called me cia leaker john kiriakou or
john kiriakou
who styles himself a whistleblower which
still makes me angry to this day
but um you know
this is just the way it is now what
what's happened since i got out of
prison
in february of 2015 is
uh all of us obama-era whistleblowers
have sort of banded together along with
some absolutely amazing attorneys like
jessalyn radak for example
formerly of the government
accountability project now of what's
called the whisper program the
whistleblower
and source protection program uh
tom drake ed snowden the godfather of
whistleblowing the great
heroic daniel ellsberg uh there are a
bunch of us
and we're like brothers and sisters and
what we do now and
i'm and i'm happy to do it and i do it
several times a week
is to advise other would-be
whistleblowers
so that they don't make the same
mistakes that i made or the same
mistakes that my other whistleblowing
colleagues uh have made
the truth has to has to get out there
and this is one thing about the truth is
it always eventually sees the light
right you can't keep you can't keep the
truth
uh under under wraps you you can't
trick the american people over the long
term
it's just not possible and so
i'm happy to be a part of helping people
get their truth
out there remember there's a legal
definition of whistleblowing
bringing to light any evidence of waste
fraud
abuse illegality or threats to the
public health
or public safety i'm going to close by
saying
one thing at the cia the culture is such
that they always taught us that
everything in life
is a shade of gray that is not true
some things are black and white some
things
are right and wrong when i stood on my
first day at the cia with my hand in the
air
and i swore an oath to uphold the
constitution of the united states
and to protect it against all enemies
foreign and domestic
i meant it i'm sorry to say that of the
300 people in the room that day
it appears that i was the only one who
meant it but i meant it
and so government is better when
government is honest
government is better when it's
transparent we're right
and they're wrong and we have to make
them pay
when they violate the law so thank you
very much
i kept it to 30 minutes just like i
promised howie
and i am happy to take whatever
questions you might have for me
oh we can't hear you howie
said thank you john i think a lot of
people hearing the details in the
sequence
just brings it home thank you because
most people
they maybe read something in the press
and you know when you string it together
you realize how
uh how oppressive the government is
toward people that
tell us what's going on that we ought to
know about
yeah and that is a huge problem i mean
it reminds me we call ourselves a
democracy reminds me of
what gandhi said when he was asked about
western civilization
he said it would be a good idea
and uh we we have a lot of things to
correct
yes we do indeed so
i've seen some questions in the chat
there we go
so santino musto my question to john did
it rattle your nerves
and or mentally scar you've seen people
being tortured
and murdered did this have anything to
do with you deciding to become a
whistleblower
that's a really good question you know
it's funny i've been answering these
questions for
you know 14 years and nobody's ever
asked me that
um the easy answer is yes
it did scar me um when i came home from
from pakistan
well let me back up i've got a friend
who i worked with in the cia we go to
the same
church and um he just happens to be
a former brigadier general and he's also
a psychiatrist
and um he mentioned something to me
about a year ago that i
it just had never crossed my mind he
said i said you know i was a star at the
agency
until until i i left and he said that's
not true
they turned on you in 2002. i said what
are you talking about
i was a star in 2002 i went up to the
seventh floor i was the executive
assistant
and he said don't you remember they used
to call you the human rights guy
i said yes he said that wasn't a
compliment
they were talking about you behind your
back because you weren't willing to
torture anybody
or to kill anybody and
another truth of that time and i kept
this to myself
um was i came back from pakistan with
with ptsd you know i was
i was surprised at
how willing my colleagues were
to kill people you know these are guys
that i used to get together with on the
weekends we'd have a barbecue our kids
would play together
our wives were friends and then they
would go on their week-long missions
and and kill people and come back
there was one guy there was one guy that
i worked with i sat 20 feet away from
him
in the cia's counterterrorism center and
every morning i'd say hey man how you
doing and every morning he'd say hey
buddy how you doing
i was never really clear on exactly what
he did in the office you know we don't
have like
name tags or anything with your job
description right
so i asked a colleague i said you know
i'm unclear
exactly what he does here he travels an
awful lot
and my friend said john he works for the
special activities division
what do you think they do and i thought
wow you know what i hadn't thought of
that
because he's such a nice guy he's so
easy going he brings
bagels in on fridays and coffee and
he was an assassin and you know when
when public opinion polls show that
the american people are in solid support
of the cia and other intelligence
agencies killing
people who they believe might perhaps
maybe someday pose a threat to the
united states
i mean where do you go from there you're
really crying in the darkness
but um yes to to answer uh santino's
question
uh yeah that was not my thing it
bothered me very much
i'll add one other thing a cia
psychiatrist a different one
once told me that the cia actively seeks
to hire people who have sociopathic
tendencies
not sociopaths sociopaths
are impossible to control because they
don't have a conscience
they blow right through the the
polygraph exam but you just
can't control them because they're
unable to feel remorse
or regret but as you might imagine
sociopaths slip through the process
because they can't feel remorse because
they don't react
on a polygraph well just like in
corporate america those
same sociopaths rise to the very top of
the cia's leadership
and that's why we've got assassination
squads
and that's why we have teams of people
who overthrow
governments or who do international
kidnapping
you know that's why we need robust
congressional oversight which we haven't
had since the
the 70s frankly good question thank you
santino
jason justice asks hi john do you know
how many publicly known quote
intelligence
agencies there are follow-up
why do we need so many when they seem to
be asleep at the switch
yeah promoters of u.s imperialism yes
you're absolutely right in every aspect
of that question jason
um first of all there are no secret
intelligence services anymore um not
since nsa finally went public the cia of
course was secret in the beginning
nsa was secret like into the late
70s uh but what you see is what you get
i think it's like 19 of them
now some are still so secret that we
don't really know what they do like
darpa for example at the pentagon
we know that they develop futuristic
weapon systems and stuff like that but
beyond
that we don't really know what goes on
inside darpa
uh why do we need so many of them we
don't
we don't this is empire building on the
part of different components of the us
government primarily the pentagon
like the pentagon is in ultimate
charge of most intelligence agencies
so why do we need army intelligence navy
intelligence marine corps intelligence
air force intelligence uh dia
uh nsa belongs to the pentagon why do we
need all those
they're duplicative they all do the same
thing
and then they try to one-up each other
and better each other all the while the
cia's making fun of them about how
terrible they are and how amateurish
but the final part of your your question
is um they seem to be asleep at the
switch and promoters of u.s imperialism
yes you're exactly right they are asleep
at the switch
and listen i'm telling you from first
hand experience
the cia which is supposed to be the
quote-unquote
best and brightest has missed literally
every major international development
since the creation of the cia
in 1947. they missed everything from
from the building of the berlin wall to
the fall of the berlin wall
and everything in between they they blew
the collapse of the uh
of the soviet union they blew the
collapse of the shah's regime in iran
the the directorate of operations
completely blew
uh democracy in iran by overthrowing
prime minister musa
on behalf of british petroleum bp
seriously kermit roosevelt for uh
teddy roosevelt's son who was in charge
of that operation for the cia
later said that it was the gravest
mistake he had made in his life
uh my dear friend and attorney bruce
fine he's
he's one of the most important uh
constitutional scholars in america
uh has been talking about writing a book
about the cia's analytic failures we all
know about their operational failures
they're terrible operationally but the
analytic failures
are even more dangerous or have been
more dangerous through history
because it's that analysis that our
policy makers rely on
to make foreign policy and frequently
the cia has been
so wrong that foreign policy has been a
disaster
a disaster so excellent question thank
you for that
yeah i would just add that there was a
book came out several years ago
by william arkin and dana priest called
top secret america
yes fantastically an expose in the
washington post
it it describes department of homeland
security and
the intelligence agencies have become
like
the military industrial companies an
intelligence industrial complex
yes building bureaucracies they got so
much money
they're spending it you know before the
end of the year so they can get
you know refunded and there's a lot of
waste and
while they're playing with all this
money they're not collecting
intelligence yes you know let me ask you
a question and this is not a rhetorical
question
why does the department of agriculture
need an intelligence agency
why does the department of commerce need
a fully staffed intelligence agency what
possible intelligence could they be
collecting or
analyzing or contributing to it doesn't
make any sense to me
you know it's like the department of
education has has an
armed uh police unit that also collects
intelligence
it's the department of education
although they're not members of the the
i
capital i capital c intelligence
community
why do they even call themselves
intelligence this doesn't make
any sense to me yeah it reminds me of
another book came out in 80s about
uh they called it guard labor one
quarter of the workforce
security guards police the intelligence
apparatus is watching the
three-quarters of us i mean it's an
enormous waste
and really not in the public interest
yeah so
yeah that's right you know ed snowden we
wouldn't have any idea really the extent
to which nsa spies on us if it hadn't
been for ed snowden
i think he's a bonafide american hero i
really do
and let's let's think about this for a
second what nsa does
first of all nsa was not created by an
act of congress
it was just arbitrarily created by the
pentagon
and just foisted upon us uh the pentagon
denied its
existence until 1978. and now
what they do despite the fact that in
nsa's charter
they are prohibited prohibited from
collecting information on what are
called u.s persons that's
a u.s citizen or any person in the
country on a green card
a permanent resident alien
that's all they do now right they have
access to every phone call every email
every text message
that every american sends and receives
every single day and they have enough
space
memory at this new facility that they
just finished building in utah
to collect information from every
american for the next 500 years
that's not what they should be doing
they should be collecting overseas to
protect us
we are not the enemy here but that's
what it's come down to
i see rob rich has a uh question about
julian assange
i'm proud to say that i'm on the julian
assange defense advisory committee
and um julian is suffering
mightily right now but i think
actually that he has the upper hand in
that
the justice department has to prove
to the british supreme court
that the the way the u.s practices
solitary confinement is not a form of
torture
now the reason why that's going to be
impossible is that the united nations
has already declared it to be a form of
torture
and two other british courts have
blocked extraditions
to the united states of prisoners
who would be subject to solitary
confinement here
because it's a form of torture
so there are three separate precedents
that are serving right now to protect
julian assange now the british are being
jerks about it
and they won't let him out of belmar's
prison pending this
this appeal but honestly i don't see how
the us can win this appeal
they're gonna have to let julian go
hope so let's hope so
z kramer do you think it is realistic to
remove the institution of the cia
thank you for that the answer is yes and
i'll i'll tell you why
um i mentioned a few minutes ago that
much intelligence work is duplicative
uh in the cia's case that's especially
true
uh the cia's depart or directorate of
intelligence does analysis
well the same literally the same
analysis is done
by the state department's bureau of
intelligence and research inr
the directorate of operations at the cia
collects human source intelligence
human source intelligence is also
collected by the defense department's
defense
human services dhs
the cia's directorate of science and
technology
develops new
new weapons new systems new
ways of interception just as both
nsa and darpa do so literally everything
that the cia does
is also done somewhere else in
government and at least
in the case of the state department and
darpa it's done
better than it's done at the cia um the
cia
in my view has become a rogue
organization especially
after 9 11. and congress
just is unwilling or unable to exercise
legitimate oversight and so i really
don't
believe that we need a cia
it doesn't contribute anything to the
national security
it it hasn't saved us from anything
protected us from anything
i mean it was the cia's failure that we
had 911 in the first place
so no i i don't think that we need to
have a cia deborah souza
oliveira john yes what can americans do
to protect whistleblowers
what a great question that is um and and
it's hard the answer is difficult
it's it's um
it's something that's going to take a
long time and what we have to do is to
ride
our elected officials uh to to
not just you know come out in support of
whistleblowers but the laws need to be
changed
how he mentioned in his his introduction
or maybe you didn't maybe how he
before we started we were talking about
it uh and
that's the fact that whistleblowers are
not permitted to present an affirmative
defense
you know i talked to ed snowden a few
months ago and we were talking about
the possibility of him coming home and
he said that that
he's willing to come home and he's
willing to go to prison
right if he can get up in court and
explain to the judge
and to the american people why he did
what he did that's called an affirmative
defense
yes i did it but i did it for this
reason
well the espionage act does not allow an
affirmative defense
and in my own case my judge said
not in a million years could i get up
and explain why i did what i did
because the affirmation is irrelevant
so what we need to do is we need to very
seriously amend and you know what i take
that back
not amend we need to scrap the espionage
act and we need to start fresh again
the espionage act is so old that it
doesn't even mention classified
information why because it was written
40 years before the classification
system was even invented
it mentions only national defense
information and then it doesn't
it doesn't identify what
national defense information is it
doesn't define it
and so it's up to each individual judge
in each
individual federal district
to define what national defense
information is
well how's that just how is that fair
so that's what we need to do is to
really ride our elected officials
now i'm not stupid i know i know that
there's
no member of congress who's gonna say oh
you know
what i should do to really win lots of
new votes
i should make it more difficult to
charge someone with espionage
but you know let's be adults here and
grab the bull by the horns
that's exactly what needs to be done the
whole law needs to be scrapped and
rewritten
and not be used against people that
aren't doing espionage that's right
listen the espionage act should be used
to prosecute people who commit espionage
against the united states
if you're working for a foreign
government china
russia cuba israel whatever
then you should be charged and
prosecuted under the espionage act
but whistleblowers no uh
eugene debs because he was against the
war
no that's not what it was meant to to be
or
that's not what it was supposed to be
anyway
diana m 16.
john do you see gitmo ever being closed
talk about
cowardice huh i'll tell you a quick
story
diane um when i caught my first group of
prisoners
it was in january of 2002 and
we locked them up temporarily in the
pindi jail
just because it happened to be the
nearest jail to us
and i called cia headquarters
counter-terrorism center and i said
listen i caught four guys
i don't know what to do with them and
they said oh we're gonna fly in a c-12
just put him on the c-12 i said oh
you're going to take it back to the u.s
for prosecution
they said no we're going to send him to
guantanamo and i said guantanamo cuba
yeah i said why would you send them to
guantanamo cuba
and the response was fascinating the
response was
we're going to use guantanamo as a
clearing house
so that we can charge them in the
federal districts
in washington dc and the eastern
district of virginia
the southern and eastern districts of
new york and the eastern district of
massachusetts
right so this is where the crimes were
committed
they're only going to be in guantanamo
for a matter of weeks until
we can figure out which district to send
them to for their trial
and i said oh that's a great idea
well nobody ever came to the united
states for trial
almost nobody was even charged with a
crime
uh you saw how the republicans
completely flipped out like crazy people
when obama said during the 2008 campaign
that he wanted to shut guantanamo down
and in fact they passed a law over his
veto threat
that prohibit the president united
states from closing down guantanamo
there was an article in today's uh
washington post saying
that the last um minor
prisoner is being released from
guantanamo he's an afghan
that leaves only one afghan left at
guantanamo
he's one of 70 people and at its height
it had something like 789 people
70 people well some of them are you know
truly bad guys like
muhammad the mastermind of 9 11. but my
god
even khalid muhammad has constitutional
rights so either charge him with a crime
or let him go same with abu zubaydah
same with ramsay ben and shib
same with all these guys if you're not
going to charge them the crime
you have to let them go they have the
same right
that you and i have to face our accusers
in a court of law
to face a jury of their peers and if
we're not going to allow them to do that
then they have to be released with that
said
i don't see guantanamo
closing down until either two things
happen
these prisoners eventually die and you
know that that happens with some
frequency
usually by suicide uh or
somehow the government is able to charge
them in a civilian court
but the reason that hasn't happened yet
is because the cia tortured them all
and because they were tortured literally
nothing that they said can be used
against them
and without their own admissions
then there's just nothing to hold them
on
it's a quagmire
tom violet uh please comment on the
recent hack
of colonial pipeline yeah um
so the government i think is saying that
it was um
it was russian i the first report i
heard was that it was
indians indian hackers uh now they're
saying it's
russian i've got a friend at the fbi who
says that they're pretty confident that
it's not
russian government it's you know
probably a handful of guys in their
parents basements or whatever
uh but uh
this is this is bad right
this is bad where a couple of hackers
could
shut down the east coast's major
pipeline
main pipeline and essentially cut off
the supply chain
of gasoline to a half a dozen states
along the east coast
but this comes back to the notion of
what nsa
should be doing why didn't nsa protect
us from this
right they're supposed to be the the
geniuses in this
in this realm where was nsa
i'll tell you where nsa was they were
busy reading your emails
and my emails and listening to our phone
calls and trying to decide
who's un-american or less american than
the next guy
but this is exactly what nsa is supposed
to be doing protecting us
from electronic enemies and they
they drop the ball
well we've come upon our hour i don't
see any more questions popping up
excellent so uh i really appreciate you
coming on john
howie thanks for having me it's always a
pleasure i've been a big fan of yours
for a long time so
i was very happy to do it thanks for
having me likewise you know i've been
following your case for a decade now and
thank you um this whistleblower issue is
so important
and you know we don't have an
administration
now any more than under trump no that is
going to deal with it i mean
fusions of julian orange and daniel hale
are going forward this is bipartisan
biden is just as bad as trump and trump
was just as bad as obama and may i say
one last thing um there's a very
important whistleblower out there right
now by the name of daniel hale
dan is the drone whistleblower who
went public with the fact that we were
murdering civilians women children the
elderly
in our drone program he
was scooped up by the justice department
last week and he's incarcerated right
now at a federal holding
facility in alexandria virginia of
course the eastern district of virginia
and um the poor guy is
terrified he's on suicide watch right
now um i posted on
facebook and on twitter his address so
you know if if you've got five minutes
send him a letter
send him a postcard just tell him that
he's not forgotten
he's really going through some dark days
right now
yeah i hope everybody will take a minute
to do that
thank you so
i don't have any closing comments you're
going to be on a podcast with uh
jessalyn radak who's a whistleblower
herself and a lawyer for whistleblowers
yes next week you want to tell people
when that's happening
sure actually let me look at my at my
calendar on my phone
jessalyn radek i mentioned a few minutes
ago was one of my attorneys one of my 11
attorneys
and um she is an absolute
genius when it comes to these these
whistleblower issues
she's a whistleblower herself she blew
the whistle on the fact that
the justice department had um
had denied access to an attorney for
john walker lind who was known as the
american taliban
uh that's gonna be at 12 noon eastern
uh go to covert action magazine's
website
uh 12 noon eastern on tuesday may 18th
okay good so if people didn't get enough
of you tonight they can
get more next week jessalyn's more
interesting than i am
and so is tom drake yeah tom drake was
one of the first
to be prosecuted and uh yes you know
he's uh
he's a hero too he is thank you
so so that's it um we're going to move
our live streams to saturday
at 3 p.m starting this saturday because
my running mate angela walker's driving
that dump truck and they've got her
working 14 hours a day
season up so she hasn't been able to
make these tuesday nights so
you know check us out on facebook and
twitter we'll be here
three o'clock on saturday and uh hope
everybody can join us
so have a good evening everybody